Welcome back to Apush in under 3
minutes. No time for intros, let's get
into it. Welcome to the Progressive Era.
Yes, it's truly time to talk about the
era following the Gilded Age. Let's
quickly define the Progressive Movement
in one sentence. Progressives responded
to political corruption, social
injustice, and economic inequality
created and heightened by industrial
capitalism and urbanization. And I don't
want you to sit there and think this
Progressive Movement was one big unified
group because it really wasn't. Rather,
it was a bunch of little movements that
had a lot of things in common, which is
why we rope them together into one big
Progressive Movement. Reformers were
often middle to upper class, and many
were women working especially in cities
and among immigrant populations. The
biggest thing you'll see in this
movement is something called muckrakers.
This means a journalist/writer who
investigates wrongdoing. Let's go
through some key figures in this regard.
Upton Sinclair was a muckraker who wrote
the famous The Jungle. This book exposed
disgusting meatpacking and pushed for
food regulations. Ida Tarbell is a
muckraker who investigated Standard Oil
and exposed their probably illegal
monopoly tactics. And finally, Jacob
Riis is a muckraker who made the book
How the Other Half Lives, where the book
is packed full of photos and reports
exposing the horrid tenement housing
conditions. Moving on, let's go over a
different section of the Progressive
Movement, the political side. Here,
we'll look at two people, Theodore
Roosevelt and Woodrow Wilson. Roosevelt
argued for a quote square deal where he
pleaded to rein in corporations, protect
consumers, and conserve natural
resources. Wilson argued for a quote
restoring economic opportunity by
breaking up monopolies, lowering
tariffs, and reforming the banking
system. Notice how both of these ideals
are trying to regulate and reform most
of what the Gilded Age stood for. That
being said, there would also be a
movement of women's rights. We already
talked about the roots of this back in
Unit 4 with the Seneca Falls Convention,
though later I did forget to mention
Susan B. Anthony, so apologies about
that. But now you have activists like
Carrie Chapman Catt and Alice Paul,
along with a lot of women rallying
behind the movement. This women's
movement will continue to grow and will
eventually contribute a lot to two
amendments later on. Now, let's move
over to African-American rights. Many
Progressives were split or simply
ignored segregation as a whole. As for
people advocating for black rights, you
have Booker T. Washington, whom we
talked about earlier, and a new one for
you, W. E. B. Du Bois, who simply
demanded full civil rights. Finally, the
last two Progressive Movements were
immigration and the environment.
Immigration exposed a split down the
middle. Some Progressives pushed
restrictions, while others focused on
supporting immigrants in cities.
Environmental reform followed a similar
pattern, dividing into preservationists
who wanted to protect nature for its own
sake and conservationists who emphasized
responsible long-term resource
management. Despite their differences,
both supported the creation of national
parks. On the screen now are AP style
questions for this topic. Pause now.
I'll put the answers on the screen now.
I will see you in the next one.